East Enders Society fonds
Simon Fraser University Archives and Records Management Department
East Enders Society fonds
1964 - 1994
F-59
Q100353798
45 cm of textual records 6 audio recordings
Simon Fraser University Archives and Records Management Department Maggie Benston Student Services Building, Rm. 0400 8888 University Dr. Burnaby British Columbia Canada V5A 1S6 Telephone: 778.782.3805 Email: archives@sfu.ca http://www.sfu.ca/archives
PHYSICAL DESCRIPTION Fonds includes 16 audio cassettes (originals and copies) and 13 .wav files.
East Enders Society
The East Enders Society was a private social service group which worked to aid women in Vancouver's East Side neighbourhoods from 1965 to 1993.
The group was initiated by Mrs. May Gutteridge, a social worker at St. James Anglican Church in the Downtown Eastside of Vancouver. In 1964, at the request of Anglican Bishop Godfrey Gower, she extended her work to include assisting native women in the courts. Through this work she saw a need for a women's hostel in Vancouver's East End. The East Enders Society was then established to provide this hostel and other services. The Society was incorporated March 24, 1965, with early members including Mrs. M. Gutteridge, Mrs. M. White, Mrs. S. Ainsworth, Miss P. Dale, Mrs. K. Arens, Mrs. M. Beckett, Miss D. Oikawa. To raise funds for the Society, a "Dollar Club" was formed, in which members contributed one dollar each month towards the Society. The East Enders were also assisted by Mary Southin (a lawyer who provided free legal advice), the United Church Women, the Anglican Church Women's Auxiliary, the Soroptomists, the Fresco Club, and various Lions Clubs. A donation of $10,000 was also received from two anonymous women from the United Church, which went toward the purchase of a rooming house at 883 East Hastings. The rooming house was refurbished and opened as a hostel in May 1965, with Mrs. Margaret White hired as matron to live at the hostel full-time. The hostel provided temporary shelter for a number of women in the Downtown Eastside. Often, women charged with drunkenness and vagrancy would be given suspended sentences, on the condition that they go to the East Enders hostel. The Society also received a monthly grant from the provincial government to hire a social worker to assist women arriving at the hostel. This hostel (sometimes referred to as the Lodge) operated for five years, then moved to 1656 East 4th Avenue, when the Hastings Street building was demolished as part of an urban renewal program. This second lodge was later sold in the mid-1970s to the Mental Patients Association, who operated it as a halfway house.
To meet the social needs of women in the area, a Women's Centre was opened at 342 East Hastings Street in 1967. The Centre provided typewriters, sewing machines, steam irons, hair washing and drying facilities, a television, a radio, a turntable, and children's toys and games. Volunteers at the Centre served tea daily, held monthly birthday parties and sponsored demonstrations and talks. This Centre later moved to 217 Dunlevy Avenue, and eventually closed in the mid-1970s.
By 1970, several other hostels were operating in the Downtown Eastside area, and social services agencies from the City of Vancouver began to request that the hostel accept long-term guests. As a result, in 1971, the hostel began taking in women who had been discharged from hospitals, but were not yet ready to live on their own.
By 1971, the Society saw a need for low-income housing for women, and began to press for the provision of such housing. In 1972, it worked to have women included in Oppenheimer Lodge (a senior citizens' housing project built by the City of Vancouver). It also assisted in the planning of other housing projects for low income women (Bauer Villa and Adanac Place). In 1974, members of the East Enders Society joined with members of the Amherst Lions Society to form the “East-Enders Amherst Lions Housing Society” to work toward providing affordable housing for senior citizens. This Society then obtained property on 3433 Renfrew St. (between 18th and 19th Avenues), where they constructed Renfrew Park Manor, a 41-unit senior citizens housing development. In the late 1970s, the Society became involved in the Franklin House Society to purchase and refurbish a vacant apartment building on 1721 Franklin Street. Two members of the East Enders Society (Margaret Davies and Mary Kelly) were executive members of the Franklin House Society, and the East Enders provided many furnishings and appliances for the building.
During the 1970s, income generated by term deposits allowed the Society to support various agencies providing housing and other services to low income women. By 1978, the Society was donating money to agencies such as Powell Place, the Y.W.C.A., Charlsford House, the Makwalla Native Women's Association, T.R.A.C.Y. (Taking Responsible Action for Children and Youth), and others.
In the 1990s, the Society began to discuss its own dissolution, and plan for distributing its assets. After accepting proposals and discussing various distribution plans, the Society was presented with a request by the Owl House Society (later renamed the Vi Fineday House Society) for financial assistance to install a $22,000 sprinkler system in the house they had just purchased for use as a shelter. The East Enders Society eventually covered the entire cost of this system, which totaled $26,827.05. Early in 1993, the Society received a proposal from the Kettle Society for a service centre for women with mental health disabilities, and it was decided that the majority of the remaining assets would go to this group. Smaller donations from the group's assets were made to Charlsford House, Children's Foundation, First United Church, St. James Anglican Church, and the Sisters of the Atonement. On October 7, 1993, the Society applied for dissolution under the Societies Act, and was formally dissolved on March 4, 1994.
published
Full
Revised
Title of the fonds is based on provenance.
Fonds consists of records arising from the general administration of the East Enders Society, and from the Society's participation in various social service projects for women in Vancouver's East Side. Fonds includes financial statements, receipts, correspondence, bulletins, reports, proposals, minutes of meetings, constitutions, job applications, letters of reference, newspaper clippings, audio tapes of interviews with Society members, partial transcripts of interviews, and other records.
The materials were arranged by the Archivist.
Sound recordings; Textual records; Health and social services; Community life; Women
The fonds was donated by one of the last members of the Society, Margaret Walker.
All accessions have been processed as of September 2002. No further accruals are expected.
Some files may contain personal or confidential information. Access to these files may be restricted as stipulated by Archives policy or the donor. Files marked 'pending review' must be reviewed by an archivist prior to release, and as a result of the review access restrictions may apply. Please see the file lists and consult the archivist for more details.
Access to the sound recordings is restricted due to the fragility of the audio cassettes; digitized access copies are available.
Series descriptions and file lists are available.
- Administration and organization, 1964 - 1994; F-59-1; 11 cm of textual records
  published
  Series consists of records arising from the establishment, organization, adminstration and dissolution of the East Enders Society. Series includes constitution, minutes, correspondence, notes, and other documents.
  - Beginnings, 1964 - 1966; F-59-1-0-0-1 (Archival box - standard 59-1)
    Textual records
    Restricted in part
  - Minutes, 1965 - 1970; F-59-1-0-0-2 (Archival box - standard 59-1)
    Restricted in whole
  - Minutes, 1971 - 1973; F-59-1-0-0-3 (Archival box - standard 59-1)
  - Minutes, 1974 - 1993; F-59-1-0-0-4 (Archival box - standard 59-1)
    Open
  - Annual meetings, 1966 - 1988; F-59-1-0-0-5 (Archival box - standard 59-1)
  - Minutes note book, 1971 - 1990; F-59-1-0-0-6 (Archival box - standard 59-1)
  - Constitution, 1965 - 1971; F-59-1-0-0-7 (Archival box - standard 59-1)
  - Board members, 1964 - 1992; F-59-1-0-0-8 (Archival box - standard 59-1)
  - Correspondence, 1964 - 1992; F-59-1-0-0-9 (Archival box - standard 59-1)
  - Dissolution, 1989 - 1994; F-59-1-0-0-10 (Archival box - standard 59-1)
- Finance, 1965 - 1993; F-59-2; 7 cm of textual records
  Series consists of records arising from fundraising, budgeting, and accounting activities of the East Enders Society. Series includes financial statements, ledgers, budgets, and correspondence.
  - Financial statements, 1965 - 1992; F-59-2-0-0-1 (Archival box - standard 59-1)
  - Funding, 1969 - 1971; F-59-2-0-0-2 (Archival box - standard 59-2)
  - Vancouver Foundation, 1969 - 1977; F-59-2-0-0-3 (Archival box - standard 59-2)
  - Treasurer's notebooks, 1968 - 1992; F-59-2-0-0-4 (Archival box - standard 59-2)
  - Final distribution of assets, 1989 - 1993; F-59-2-0-0-5 (Archival box - standard 59-2)
  - Financial ledger and statements, 1971 - 1986; F-59-2-0-0-6
  - Financial ledger and statements, 1987 - 1993; F-59-2-0-0-7
- Personnel, 1967 - 1973; F-59-3; 3 cm of textual records
  Series consists of records arising from the hiring of house mothers and social workers for the East Enders Society hostels. Series includes correspondence, lists of applicants, letters of reference, job descriptions, social worker's reports, statistics on hostel guests, and other materials.
  - Social workers, 1967 - 1973; F-59-3-0-0-1 (Archival box - standard 59-2)
  - House mothers, 1970 - 1972; F-59-3-0-0-2 (Archival box - standard 59-2)
- Newsletters, 1966 - 1990; F-59-4; 1 cm of textual records; Predominant date of material is 1966-1978.
  Series consists primarily of newsletters from the East Enders Society. Includes two newsletters from the Battered Women's Support Services.
  - Newsletters, 1966 - 1990; F-59-4-0-0-1 (Archival box - standard 59-2)
- Society history, 1990 - 1993; F-59-5; 4 cm of textual records 6 sound recordings; Physical description: series includes 16 audio cassettes (originals and copies).
  In the early 1990s, a member of the Kettle Society undertook a project to write the history of the East Enders Society. As part of this project, she interviewed several members of the Society and partial transcriptions of the audio taped interviews were completed. Members of the Society also submitted notes and proposals for book sections. The book project was eventually abandoned before the Society was officially dissolved in 1994. Series includes audio taped interviews, partial transcripts of interviews, notes and correspondence.
  Access to original cassettes is restricted due to the fragility of the media; digitized access copies are available. Consult the reference archivist for more information.
  - Adams, Mrs. Catherine Ferrie interview, 1992; F-59-5-0-0-0-1 (Audio cassette OBJ-3122, Audio cassette OBJ-3123)
    Sound recordings; Records in electronic form (digitized)
    OBJ-3123 is a copy of OBJ-3122 and was not digitized.
    Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: C-59-5-0-1.1 (orig), F-59-item1, F-59-item2.
    - OBJ-3122_SideA.wav
    - OBJ-3122_SideB.wav
  - Gutteridge, Mrs. May interview, 1992; F-59-5-0-0-0-2 (Audio cassette OBJ-3124, Audio cassette OBJ-3125)
    Gutteridge, May Cecilia; Sound recordings; Records in electronic form (digitized)
    OBJ-3125 is a copy of OBJ-3124 and was not digitized.
    Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: C-59-5-0-2.1 (orig), F-59-item3, F-59-item4.
    - OBJ-3124_SideA.wav
    - OBJ-3124_SideB.wav
  - Martin, A. interview, 1992; F-59-5-0-0-0-3 (Audio cassette OBJ-3126, Audio cassette OBJ-3127, Audio cassette OBJ-3128)
    Martin, A.; Sound recordings; Records in electronic form (digitized)
    OBJ-3127 side B is blank.
    Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: C-59-5-0-3.1 (orig), F-59-item5, F-59-item6, F-59-item7.
    - OBJ-3126_SideA.wav
    - OBJ-3126_SideB.wav
    - OBJ-3127_SideA.wav
  - Thomas, Wilma interview, 1992; F-59-5-0-0-0-4 (Audio cassette OBJ-3129, Audio cassette OBJ-3130, Audio cassette OBJ-3131)
    Wilma Thomas; Sound recordings; Records in electronic form (digitized)
    OBJ-3129 and OBJ-3131 are copies of OBJ-3130 and were not digitized. Side B of OBJ-3130 is blank.
    Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: C-59-5-0-4.1 (orig), F-59-item8, F-59-item9, F-59-item10.
    - OBJ-3130_SideA.wav
  - Wilson, Winnie interview, 1992; F-59-5-0-0-0-5 (Audio cassette OBJ-3132, Audio cassette OBJ-3133)
    Winnie Wilson; Sound recordings; Records in electronic form (digitized)
    OBJ-3133 is a copy of OBJ-3132 and was not digitized.
    Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: C-59-5-0-5.1 (orig), F-59-item11, F-59-item12.
    - OBJ-3132_SideA.wav
    - OBJ-3132_SideB.wav
  - Veil, Mrs. interview, 1990; F-59-5-0-0-0-6 (Audio cassette OBJ-3134, Audio cassette OBJ-3135, Audio cassette OBJ-3136, Audio cassette OBJ-3137)
    Mrs Veil; Sound recordings; Records in electronic form (digitized)
    OBJ-3136 and OBJ-3137 are copies and were not digitized. Side B of OBJ-3135 is blank.
    Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: C-59-5-0-6.1 (orig), F-59-item13, F-59-item14, F-59-item15, F-59-item16.
    - OBJ-3134_SideA.wav
    - OBJ-3134_SideB.wav
    - OBJ-3135_SideA.wav
  - History book suggestions, 1990 - 1993; F-59-5-0-0-1 (Archival box - standard 59-2)
  - Interview with Mrs. Catherine Ferry Adams, [ca 1992]; F-59-5-0-0-2 (Archival box - standard 59-2)
    Pending review
  - Memories, [ca 1990] - [ca 1992]; F-59-5-0-0-3 (Archival box - standard 59-3)
  - Transcripts, [ca 1990] - [ca 1992]; F-59-5-0-0-4 (Archival box - standard 59-3)
- Service projects, 1964 - 1993; F-59-6; 11 cm of textual records
  Series consists of records arising from the Society's involvement in various projects serving women and other individuals in Vancouver's East End. These activities include projects operated primarily by the Society (such as the Hostel and the Women's Centre), projects in which Society members were actively involved (such as Franklin House and Renfrew Park Manor), and projects and groups for which the Society provided financial support (such as the Kettle Friendship Society and the Vi Fineday Family Shelter Society). Series includes correspondence, brochures, bulletins, requests for funds, proposals, receipts, thank-you cards, and other materials.
  - Hostels, 1964 - 1990; F-59-6-0-0-1 (Archival box - standard 59-3)
  - Housing concerns, 1964 - 1993; F-59-6-0-0-2 (Archival box - standard 59-3)
  - Alcohol, drug education services, 1966 - 1991; F-59-6-0-0-3 (Archival box - standard 59-3)
  - Women's day centres, 1969 - 1973; F-59-6-0-0-4 (Archival box - standard 59-3)
  - Vi Fineday Family Shelter Society (formerly Owl House), 1974 - 1992; F-59-6-0-0-5 (Archival box - standard 59-3)
  - Renfrew Park Manor, 1976 - 1993; F-59-6-0-0-6 (Archival box - standard 59-3)
  - Charlsford House, 1977 - 1993; F-59-6-0-0-7 (Archival box - standard 59-3)
  - Miscellaneous gifts or support, 1977 - 1993; F-59-6-0-0-8 (Archival box - standard 59-3)
  - Young Women's Christian Association, 1978 - 1986; F-59-6-0-0-9 (Archival box - standard 59-3)
  - Taking Responsible Action for Youth, 1980 - 1982; F-59-6-0-0-10 (Archival box - standard 59-3)
  - Camps, 1982 - 1993; F-59-6-0-0-11 (Archival box - standard 59-3)
  - St. James Anglican Church, 1982 - 1993; F-59-6-0-0-12 (Archival box - standard 59-3)
  - First United Church Vancouver, 1982 - 1993; F-59-6-0-0-13 (Archival box - standard 59-3)
  - Franciscan Sisters, 1985 - 1993; F-59-6-0-0-14 (Archival box - standard 59-3)
  - Children's Foundation, 1988 - 1993; F-59-6-0-0-15 (Archival box - standard 59-3)
  - Kettle Friendship Society, 1992 - 1993; F-59-6-0-0-16 (Archival box - standard 59-3)